All right, the משנה mishna is דף צז daf tzadik zayin and
we are in the middle about 20 lines down where it's at
the two dots ארבע סניפין של זהב היו שם. arba snifin shel
zahav hayu sham. There were four branches as I guess סניפין, snifin,
but the four poles of gold the משנה mishna is describing what
was on top of the שולחן, shulchan, the framework for the bread.
These are the vertical pieces. מנלן הני מילי? menalan hanei milei? How
do I know that these existed?
אמר רב קטינא, amar rav katina, רב קטינא rav katina says אמר
קרא, amar kra, the
פסוק pasuk says ועשית קערתיו וכפתיו וקשותיו ומנקיותיו.
ve’asita ke’arotav vekapotav ukesotav
umenakiotav. I would translate the קערה ke’ara as a dish, כפה kafa
as a spoon, קשותיו kesotav I wouldn't know how to translate that,
and מנקיותיו menakiotav I would have thought like the implements to clean
it. But that's not how the גמרא gemara takes it. גמרא gemara
says as follows: קערתיו, ke’arotav, what are the קערות? ke’arot? אלו דפוסים,
elu dfusin, that's the kind of the
frame. כפתיו, kapotav, what are the spoons? אלו בזיכין, elu bezichin, these
are the spoons that were used for the לבונה. levona. קשותיו, kesotav,
אלו סניפין, elu snifin, that's this framework that we're talking
about. ומנקיותיו, umenakiotav, אלו קנים, elu kanim, those are the rods that
we talked about that separate the loaves of לחם. lechem. אשר יסך
בהן, asher yusach bahen, and these are the things the קנים kanim
which you אשר יסך בהן. asher yusach bahen. What does that mean?
שמסככין בהן את הלחם, shemesach’chin bahen et halechem, that you cover the
bread with all these things. מתיב רבא. metiv rava. רבא rava asked,
לא סידור הקנים ולא נטילתן דוחה את השבת. lo sidur hakanim velo
netilatan docha et hashabbat. We have a principle that neither the arranging
the rods or taking them off of the bread is דוחה שבת.
docha shabbat. As you know the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim was the
fresh bread was replaced the old bread every
שבת. shabbat. And רבא rava is saying, or רבא rava is quoting
that you couldn't
arrange the rods on שבת. shabbat. ואי סלקא דעתך דאורייתא, ve’i salka
datach de’oraita, now if you want to say that these words in
the תורה torah are referring to the קנים kanim and so that's
part of the עבודת בית המקדש, avodat beit hamikdash, אמאי לא דוחה
את השבת? amai lo docha et hashabbat? Everything that you had to
do in the בית המקדש beit hamikdash was דוחה שבת, docha shabbat,
right? I mean obviously the burning of sacrifices and so on, that's
all not שבת shabbat activity and yet in the מקדש mikdash you
could do it if it was part of the
עבודה. avoda. How can you say that קשותיו kesotav means that these
words are all referring to parts of the framework for the bread?
It can't be that it's דאורייתא. de’oraita. הדר אמר רבא, hadar amar
rava, but רבא rava said no, I was wrong. לא מילתא היא,
lav milta hi, that wasn't a good thing that I said. דאמרי
דתנן, de’amrei detnan, כלל אמר רבי עקיבא. klal amar rabbi akiva. Why?
Because we have a משנה mishna that רבי עקיבא rabbi akiva says
here's a
principle: כל מלאכה שאפשר לעשותה מערב שבת אינה דוחה את השבת. kol
melacha she’efshar la’asotah me’erev shabbat einah docha et hashabbat. True, in the
מקדש mikdash if you had to do עבודה avoda on שבת, shabbat,
that was דוחה שבת. docha shabbat. But if it's something that could
have been done before שבת, shabbat, that wasn't allowed to be done
on שבת. shabbat. והני נמי אפשר דלא דחי שבת עליהו. vehanai nami
efshar delo dachi shabbat aleihu.
And these rods, it's possible that you could do them before שבת
shabbat and they wouldn't be דוחה שבת. docha shabbat. How do I
know you could do it before שבת? shabbat? טעמא מאי? ta’ama mai?
Why do we even use these rods? דלא ליעפש לחם, delo liy’apesh
lechem, so the bread doesn't, the loaves don't sit on each other
and that would cause them to get moldy. אבל בהאי שיעורא לא
מיעפש, aval behei shi’ura lo mi’apesh, but in the short time over
שבת shabbat that they would be sitting on each other, that's not
enough time for them to get moldy. That you could do before
שבת shabbat and after שבת shabbat you could separate them with the
rods.
Didn't we say there was a miracle anyway that they stayed fresh
and would be shown
regularly as they were done any time in the last few days,
right?
Okay, and what was the procedure so that it wouldn't be they
wouldn't be sitting on top of each other for too long? כדתניא,
kedatanya, we have a ברייתא: braita: כיצד? keitzad? How would the rod
assembly be done? נכנס מערב שבת, nichnas me’erev shabbat, the כהן kohen
would come in on ערב שבת erev shabbat ושמטן veshamtan and he
would remove the rods from the bread ומניחן לארכו של שולחן umani’chan
le’orcho shel shulchan and he'd put them down along the length of
the שולחן, shulchan, presumably on the floor.
ומוצאי שבת, umotza’ei shabbat, and after שבת shabbat נכנס nichnas he would
come in מגביה ראשה של חלה, magbi’a rasha shel challah, he would
lift up the corner, the edge of the חלה, challah, of each
חלה challah ומכניס קנה תחתיה umachnis kaneh tachteha and slip in one
of these rods underneath. וחוזר ומגביה ראשה של חלה ומכניס קנה תחתיה,
vechozer umagbi’a rasha shel challah umachnis kaneh tachteha, and he would do
that for each of the loaves.
That's how it ended up being done, the rods would be removed
before שבת shabbat and replaced after שבת shabbat and you wouldn't have
to do that on שבת. shabbat. And this was not, so it's
really only half a day for each of the sets of loaves
to be without the rods, and that's not enough time for them
to get moldy.
And by the way, a few more details, ארבע חלות. Arba challos.
How do you get the half a day?
Oh, because, because they would be changed in the middle of the
day, right? So the first half of the day, I mean I'm
not being precise, but the first half of the day was the
old loaves and then the new loaves. Okay. ארבע חלות Arba challos
and now we're a few more details about this, ארבע חלות צריכות
שלשה שלשה קנים. arba challos tzerichos shelosha shelosha kanim.
Four of the חלות, challos, so remember they're in two sets of
six, right? So you have a stack, two stacks of six loaves.
So four of those loaves would need three rods underneath them to
separate them. העליונה, Ha'elyonah, the top one, אינה צריכה אלא שנים, einah
tzerichah ela shenayim, would only need two rods underneath it. Why? לפי
שאינה לה משאוי, lefi she'einah lah masoi, because it doesn't have the
weight of additional loaves on top of it. So the weight of
only the one loaf, it's enough to have two rods separating it
from the one underneath it. However, the next four had more weight
on top of them, so they would need three rods. And what
about the bottom one?
התחתונה אינה צריכה כל עיקר. Hatachtonah einah tzerichah kol ikar. Underneath the
bottom loaf, you don't need any rods because it's not being separated,
it's not on top of another loaf. What's it on top of?
לפי שהוא מונח על טהרו של שלחן, lefi shehu munach al taharo
shel shulchan, it's directly on the שלחן shulchan itself.
And the assumption is, רש"י Rashi says about טהרו של שלחן taharo
shel shulchan somewhere that it's cold. Yeah, על טהרו של שלחן al
taharo shel shulchan ולא מיעפשי, v'lo mi'afshi, he just says straight out
that it's because it's on the table, it's when the warm bread
is against the warm bread that we're worried about becoming moldy, but
if it's on the metal table, the golden שלחן, shulchan, it doesn't
get moldy. And the שיטה מקובצת Shita Mekubetzes over here on the
left side in my edition, י"ב, yud-bais, says שלחן דקריר, shulchan d'karir,
because it's cool. The metal is cool and so it's not going
to cause it to become moldy. Okay.
תנן התם. Tnan hatam. Now we have, so now we're going to
digress from the dimensions and the details of the שלחן shulchan to
the מזבח. mizbeiach. רבי מאיר אומר: Rabbi Meir omer: כל אמות שהיו
במקדש
בינוניות. kol amos she'hayu bamikdash beinoniyos. All of the אמות amos used
in measuring in the מקדש mikdash were the middle,
I wouldn't say average, I'd say the middle, because there's, we're going
to see later that there were אמות amos of חמשה טפחים, chamisha
tefachim, ששה טפחים, shisha tefachim, and שבעה טפחים. shiva tefachim. Right now
we're just going to deal with the five and six. So the
בינוני beinoni is the six. So all, he's saying all of the
אמות amos used in the מקדש mikdash were the ששה טפח shisha
tefach kind of אמה, amah, חוץ ממזבח הזהב, chutz m'mizbeach hazahav, except
for the מזבח הזהב, mizbeach hazahav, that's the inside מקדש mikdash מזבח
mizbeach for the קטורת, ketores, והקרן, v'hakaren, and the corner of the
מזבח העולה, mizbeach ha'olah, והסובב, v'hasovev,
and the ledge, that's the middle part of the
מזבח, mizbeiach, והיסוד, v'hayesod, and the base of the מזבח. mizbeiach. Those
were all measured not with the בינוני, beinoni, so we'll see then
he means not with the ששה טפח shisha tefach measure, but with
the חמשה טפח chamisha tefach measure, those specific exceptions. רבי יהודה אומר:
Rabbi Yehuda omer: אמת בנין ששה טפחים. amas binyan shisha tefachim. Rabbi
Yehuda says no, the construction, anything made and used in construction was
the ששה טפח אמה, shisha tefach amah, ושל כלים חמשה, v'shel kelim
chamisha, but when we're talking about putting together the כלים kelim of
the מזבח, mizbeiach, the כלי שרת, klei shares, those were using a
חמשה טפח chamisha tefach measure. אמר רבי יוחנן משניהם מקרא אחד דרשו.
Amar Rabbi Yochanan misheneihem mikra echad darshu. Both of them get their
opinions from one from the same פסוק. pasuk. What's the פסוק? pasuk?
Now this is a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל, Yechezkel, and we have
to, I think, suspend our regular reading skills, shall we say, and
it is יחזקאל Yechezkel after all, so we'll see how the גמרא
Gemara parses this פסוק. pasuk. The
פסוק pasuk is: ואלה מדות המזבח באמות אמה אמה וטפח וחיק האמה
ואמה רוחב וגבולה אל שפתה סביב זרת האחד וזה גב המזבח. v'eileh
middos hamizbeiach ba'amos amah amah vatofach v'cheik ha'amah v'amah rochav u'gevulah el
sfatah saviv zeres ha'echad v'zeh gav hamizbeiach. Okay, let's take apart this
פסוק pasuk in a semi-normal way first. ואלה מדות המזבח, v'eileh middos
hamizbeiach,
these are the measurements of the מזבח, mizbeiach, באמות, ba'amos, measured in
אמות. amos. באמות אמה, ba'amos amah, the גמרא Gemara will interpret this
as in medium אמות. amos. אמה וטפח, amah vatofach, which is one
אמה amah and a טפח, tefach, which the גמרא Gemara will interpret
as a regular אמה amah is five, or standard אמה amah is
five, so the medium אמה amah is five plus one טפח, tefach,
or six. וחיק האמה... v'cheik ha'amah... חיק האמה cheik ha'ama, *cheik ha'ama*,
the חיק *cheik* is going to be interpreted as the base, ואמה
רוחב *ve'ama rochev*, and then there's something about an אמה amah *ama*
of width, וגבולה אל שפתו סביב *ugevula el sfaso saviv*, and the
distance from to the border to the to the end, we'll see
that's talking about probably talking about the קרן keren *keren*, זרת האחד
*zeres ha'echad*, that width is one זרת *zeres*, which a זרת *zeres*
is a half an אמה amah *ama*, וזה גב המזבח *veze gav
hamizbe'ach*. We'll see how the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* interprets that. This is
the top of the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach*. All right, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* is going to try and figure this all out.
Okay, so we're five lines down from the top on צדיק זיין
עמוד ב *tzadik zayin amud bais*. רבי מאיר סבר *Rabbi Meir savar*
זהו *zehu* when it says זה גב המזבח *ze gav hamizbe'ach*, זה
מזבח mizbe'ach, הסבר *ze mizbe'ach hasbar*, רבי מאיר סבר זהו באמה בת
חמישה *Rabbi Meir savar zehu be'ama bas chamisha*. Rabbi Meir says when
it says זה גב המזבח *ze gav hamizbe'ach*, this top of the
מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbe'ach* and all the things we mentioned here is the
five טפח אמה tefach amah. *tafach ama*. הכל אמות amos כלים Keilim
באמה בת שש *hakol amos keilim be'ama bas shesh*. When it says
זה *ze* it means only this, right, only these specific measurements that
it just listed about the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbe'ach* are the five טפח
אמות tefach amos? *tafach amos*, so everything else, all the other כלים
Keilim *keilim* in the מקדש *Mikdash* were six, six טפח אמות tefach
amos. *tafach amos*. רבי יהודה סבר כזה יהיו כל אמות amos *Rabbi
Yehuda savar kaze yihyu kol amos*. He interprets the same phrase זה
גב המזבח *ze gav hamizbe'ach* differently, says זה *ze* means like כזה
*kaze*, just as this מזבח mizbe'ach? *mizbe'ach* measurements were five טפח אמות
tefach amos. *tafach amos*, so too the other כלים *keilim* were also
using these five טפח tefach אמות amos *tafach amos*. So now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to try and follow what's going on
here in this פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* in יחזקאל Yechezkel, *Yechezkel*. קסלקא דעתך
*kasalka da'atach*, so their first assumption is מיסוד ועד סובב sovev. באמה
בת חמישה בגובה *mi'yesod ve'ad sovev be'ama bas chamisha begova*.
The first part of the פסוק pasuk. *pasuk* is saying that from
the
base to the סובב sovev, *sovev*, to the middle part of the
מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbe'ach*, we're talking about five טפח tefach אמות amos *tafach
amos*. ומה חיק האמה ואמה רוחב cheik ha'amah ve'amah rochav, *umai cheik
ha'ama ve'ama rochev*, what does the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* mean when it
says חיק האמה cheik ha'amah, ואמה רוחב *cheik ha'ama ve'ama rochev*, הכי
קאמר *hachi ka'amar*. This is what it means: מחיק האמה *mecheik ha'ama*
from the, I don't even know how to translate this, from the
lap, what's he translating here, the base, from the base ועד רוחב
*ve'ad rochev* until the width, in other words as you go up
the side until you get, as you
go up
the vertical until you get to a horizontal level, right, because it's
like stairs almost,
until you get to a horizontal surface, then we're using באמה בת
חמישה *be'ama bas chamisha*.
So it's the wider on top? It's wide, well it's not wider
on top but different measurement on top. So the first, in other
words, the first, and where do we get to that first horizontal
surface? After the יסוד yesod *yesod*, right? We start with the יסוד
yesod, *yesod*, it's one אמה ama *ama* high, and then there's a
part of the horizontal surface is exposed and then you start with
the סובב sovev, *sovev*, right? So in other words, when do you
use the five טפח tefach
אמות amos, *tafach amos*?
No, you didn't walk on it, that was just the way it
was built, and you
went up the כבש *kevesh*. Oh, the ramp. But then you could
get off at different places when you went up the...
Well, when you went up the ramp you could get off on
the, on the very top or on the סובב sovev *sovev*. Not
the יסוד yesod. *yesod*, I don't think anybody ever walked on the
יסוד yesod, *yesod*. The יסוד yesod. *yesod* was only one אמה ama
*ama* off the ground, that was the base, but I don't think
anybody ever walked on that.
So there were those... so then ignoring the סובב sovev *sovev* there
were two levels. Correct, right.
All right, so, so when are we talking about the five טפח
tefach אמות amos, *tafach amos*? מחיק האמה *mecheik ha'ama* from the base
ועד רוחב *ve'ad rochev* and until you got to a place where
there was a width, a width to walk on, in other words
just the יסוד *yesod*.
One second,
not just the יסוד *yesod*, actually the סובב sovev *sovev* also. Hold
on one second.
Yeah,
I'm sorry, I misstated. The place where you have the width of
an אמה ama *ama* would be...
ah, so he's saying from the base until the next ledge, okay,
which is until the top of the סובב sovev. *sovev*, that's where
you use your five טפח tefach אמות amos. *tafach amos*. All right,
now let's do the calculations.
כמה הוי עשר אמות? amos The whole מזבח mizbe'ach. we know was
ten אמות amos. high. שיש בני חמישה חמישה Shish b'nei chamisha chamisha
וארבעי בני שיתא שיתא. v'arba'i b'nei shita shita. So, according to this
interpretation of the פסוק, pasuk the first six אמות amos were of
five טפחים tepachim each, because first you have one אמה ama, of
the base, and then five אמות amos, of the סובב. sovev, So,
that's six אמות amos, were measured in five טפח tefach אמות, amos
and then the rest of it,
וארבעי בני שיתא שיתא, v'arba'i b'nei shita shita, and four, the rest
of the height of the מזבח, mizbe'ach which is four אמות, amos
would be measured as six טפח tefach אמות. amos מזבח כמה הוי,
Mizbe'ach kama haveh, so how much is the total height of the
מזבח mizbe'ach? in טפחים? tepachim? So, you have six times five is
thirty, and four times six is twenty-four,
right? So, that's fifty-four. הוי חמשים וארבע. Haveh chamshin v'arba. So, there's
fifty-four טפחים, tepachim, the total height of the מזבח. mizbe'ach Why is
this important?
פלגא דמזבח כמה הוי עשרין ושבעה. Palga d'mizbe'ach kama haveh esrin v'shiv'ah.
מקרנות ועד סובב. Mi'karnos v'ad sovev. How much is
half of the height of the מזבח? mizbe'ach Half of fifty-four is
twenty-seven. Now, why is this important? Because we're going to, some of
the מתנות דם matnos dam had to be on the upper part
of the מזבח, mizbe'ach. and some had to be on the lower
part of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. All right, now,
so so far we've got the מזבח mizbeach. is fifty-four טפחים tepachim
according to this way of interpreting the פסוק. pasuk Halfway up is
twenty-seven.
מקרנות ועד סובב כמה הוי? Mi'karnos v'ad sovev kama haveh? What about
from the top of the horns until the סובב, sovev, how much
is that? עשרין וארבעה. Esrin v'arba'ah. That's four times six is twenty-four,
right? Four אמות amos, times six. כמה בציר לפלגא דמזבח? Kama batzir
l'palga d'mizbe'ach? So, how much higher than that is the סובב, sovev,
the top of the סובב sovev, from the halfway point of the
מזבח? mizbeach The difference between twenty-four and twenty-seven, right? Three טפחים. tepachim.
So, you've got the סובב sovev, up here at the height of
twenty-four from the top and three further down is the halfway mark
of the whole thing. Okay, I shouldn't have done that, now I
lost my place.
כמה בציר לפלגא דמזבח תלתא. Kama batzir l'palga d'mizbe'ach tlata. How much
is left from the סובב sovev, going down to the halfway point?
Three טפחים. tepachim. So, all right, so far so good. והתנן, V'hatnan,
we have a משנה. mishnah. חוט של סיקרא חוגרו באמצע כדי להבדיל
בין דמים העליונים לדמים התחתונים. Chut shel sikra chogro b'emtza k'dei l'havdil
bein damim ha'elyonim l'damim hatachtonim. There was a red line that marked
the halfway point of the מזבח mizbeach, so you would know to
put the blood that had to go on the upper half of
the מזבח mizbeach. above the line, otherwise below the line.
סיקרא Sikra means red?
I thought so, but I could be wrong.
I don't remember. I thought it was painted, that's what I...
Just a second. חוט של סיקרא. Chut shel sikra. Good question.
Let's see how they translate this.
Yeah, it says here red line.
A line of red. Okay.
So, they like painted it? Yeah.
Okay, they're not telling us what they used to
paint it.
It's
just because it's blood, that's interesting to me
that it would be red.
Well, it would match.
Yeah, but if it wasn't made of blood, it would wash off
each day, wouldn't it? I mean, yeah, but then the blood would
match the
line and maybe there would be some confusion. I don't know.
The blood splattering was probably pretty not so precise like a straight
line.
But now there were times when you had to sprinkle blood above
the halfway mark. We had that, right? Right.
So, that's going to be important, what... Yeah. All right, so so
far we have no problems, we just, we've set up all the
dimensions. אלא דתניא, Ela d'tanya, but now we have a ברייתא braisa
regarding עולת העוף. olas ha'of. עולת העוף, Olas ha'of, which had to
be done on the top, the blood had to be sprinkled on
the top part of the מזבח. mizbeach, So, what was the procedure?
היה עולה בכבש, Haya oleh b'kevesh, he would go up the ramp.
ופונה לסובב, U'foneh l'sovev, and then he would turn off the main
ramp and get off at the first level, the סובב. sovev ובא
לו לקרן דרומית מזרחית, U'ba lo l'keren dromis mizrachis, he came to
the southeast corner. ומולק את ראשה, U'molek es rosha, he would do
the מליקה, melika, cut the head off. ממול ערפה ומבדיל, Mimul orpah
u'mavdil, behind the neck and separate the head from the body. וממצה
את דמו על קיר המזבח, U'mamatze es damo al kir hamizbe'ach, and
he would squeeze the blood on the wall of the מזבח. mizbe'ach
So, he's standing on the סובב, sovev so he's already above the
halfway point, so we're fine, right? Now, ואם עשה למטה מרגליו אפילו
אמה אחת כשרה. V'im asah l'mata meraglav afilu amah achas kesherah. If
he bent over below where his feet were,
even a full אמה ama. below his feet, in other words below
the top of the סובב, sovev, כשרה, kesherah, it's okay. Ah, so
now we have our problem, right? Because we just said that the
halfway... halfway mark was how far below the סובב, sovev. the surface
of the סובב, sovev. three טפחים. tefachim. And this ברייתא braisa is
telling us that you could actually do the the blood of the
bird that has to be on the top half a full אמה
ama, below the top of the סובב, sovev. right? Which is below
the halfway mark, because an אמה ama is either five or six
טפחים. tefachim. So we're talking about, so the ברייתא braisa would be
saying effectively, if our calculations are correct, then the ברייתא braisa is
allowing him to go an אמה ama down from the surface of
the סובב, sovev. which is below the halfway mark. So we must
our calculations must be wrong. So as the גמרא Gemara says, הכא
יהא עליונה למטה משני טפחים.
hacha yehei elyona
lemata mishnei tefachim. You could be two טפחים tefachim too low
from the halfway mark. So how could that be? אלא, ella, so
we have to reinterpret our measurements. So forget everything you knew about
what how we interpreted יחזקאל, Yechezkel. and here's a new interpretation. חיק
האמה כניסה. cheik ha'ama kenisa. When
the נביא navi says חיק האמה, the base was an אמה, ama
it means
the indentation from the side. In other words, the surface of the
exposed surface of the יסוד was one five-טפח אמה. tefach amah
אמה רוחב, ama rochav, and then when it says a width of
an אמה, ama כניסה, kenisa, it also means the indentation. In other
words, the horizontal measure, not a vertical measure, is what we're talking
about for these five-טפח tefah אמות. amos אל
שפתה סביב, el sfatah saviv, and when it says again the measurement
from the קרן keren to the middle of the קרן keren to
the edge, כניסה kenisa is also the indentation. So now let's redo
the calculations. מזבח כמה הוי ליה, mizbeach kama havei lei, שישים. shishim.
So therefore all of the vertical measurements of אמות amos, are six-טפח
tefah אמות, amos so 10 times 6 is 60. Okay. פלגא דמזבח
כמה הוי, palga demizbeach kama havei, so what's the halfway point? שלושים.
sheloshim. So it's 30. 30 is the halfway mark. מקרנות ועד סובב
כמה הוי, mikarnot ve'ad sovev kama havei, from the top of the
קרנות karnot until the surface of the סובב sovev, is four אמות,
amos, which is 24. 4 times 6 is 24. הוי כ"ד. havei
kaf-dalet. כמה בציר לפלגא דמזבח, kama batzir lepalga demizbeach, how much is
the space between the surface of the סובב sovev, down to the
halfway mark? The difference between 24 and 30, which is six. שישה,
shisha, which is good. ודתנן ואם עשה למטה מרגליו אפילו אמה אחת
כשרה. udtnan ve'im asa lemata meraglav afilu ama achat keshera.
And the משנה Mishna said if you did it one אמה ama
below where you were standing, in other words one אמה ama below
the surface of the סובב, sovev then you're still in the top
half, you're still good.
So that seems to come out okay, right? Right.
Yes.
That makes more sense this way.
Right. Also like why would you, you know why would you use
halfway up use one measure and and the right that doesn't make
much sense either, but as I said, we're talking about יחזקאל. Yechezkel
So but now the גמרא Gemara has a different question. במאי אוקימתא
בכניסה? bemai okimta bekenisa? So you want to say that the five-טפח
אמה tefach amah, is talking about the horizontal measure, not the vertical
measure, right? The indentation. ומי מצית מוקמת לה בכניסה? umi matzit mokmat
lah bekenisa? Can you really do that? Now we're going to try
and and measure the surface area rather than the height of the
מזבח. mizbe'ach Okay.
והתניא, vehatanya, מזבח היה ל"ב על ל"ב. mizbeach haya lamed-bet al lamed-bet.
The מזבח mizbe'ach measured 32 אמה ama, by 32 אמה ama
surface area we're talking now. עלה אמה וכנס אמה זהו יסוד. ala
ama vechanas ama zehu yesod. Oh yeah,
it goes up one אמה ama. and indents one אמה, ama, that's
the יסוד, that's the base, right? נמצא
ל' על ל'. nimtza lamed al lamed. Now we've got what do
we have left? 30 by 30, right? Because you have one אמה
ama. on each of two directions the base of the יסוד.
So now we're back now we're down to 30 by 30 for
the surface area. ושני טפחים הוי. veshenei tefachim havei.
Oh, sorry, נמצא
ל' ושני טפחים הוי.
nimtza lamed veshenei
tefachim havei.
But actually it's not exactly 30, it's 30 plus two טפחים tefachim
because if we're assuming, this is this is really confusing, but we're
assuming that when the גמרא Gemara talks about אמות amos. it means
the average six-טפח tefah אמה. ama. When יחזקאל's Yechezkel? talking about the
special אמות amos used for the horizontal measurement that's five, so we're
actually not removing two full אמות amos of six, we're removing five
טפחים tefachim each way, right? So what are we left with when
we subtract from thirty-two by thirty-two? We don't have thirty by thirty,
we have thirty plus two טפחים tefachim left.
Right? Okay, because we haven't removed, we haven't subtracted a six טפח
tefach אמה, ama we've only subtracted a five טפח tefach אמה. ama
So dealing with our standard אמות, amos we still have thirty plus
two
טפחים. tefachim. ותו
עלה חמש וכנס אמה, v'tu ala hamesh v'kanas ama, and then furthermore
we're going up and it goes up five אמות amos and indents
one
אמה. ama This is the סובב. sovev Okay, so again we're going
to do the same thing, נמצא עשרים ושמונה על עשרים ושמונה. nimtza
esrim u'shmona al esrim u'shmona. So if you just use regular אמה
ama calculations, now we've got instead of thirty by thirty, we've got
twenty-eight by twenty-eight because we've subtracted another אמה ama of surface area
by the indentation of the סובב. sovev, But the גמרא Gemara protests,
עשרים ושמונה וארבעה טפחים הוו. esrim u'shmona v'arbaa tefachim havu.
So now we're again another two טפחים tefachim in difference between
these two kinds of measurements. So now we're down to not really
twenty-eight אמות, amos but twenty-eight אמות amos plus four טפחים, tefachim, right?
Two that we lost in this strange, in the non-standard measurement indenting
from the יסוד, and another two that we lost from the non-standard
measurement indenting from the סובב. Okay, so וכי תימא, vechi teima, so
why, so we're saying that the משנה Mishna is not being precise,
right? It shouldn't say it's twenty-eight, it should say it's twenty-eight plus
four טפחים. tefachim. וכי תימא כיון דלא הוי אמה לא חשיב ליה.
vechi teima keivan d'la havi ama lo chashiv lei. And now, so
what are you going to tell me? That it's only counting full
אמות, amos right? We're rounding down. So that's why it says twenty-eight,
it's not being so precise.
All right, but how about go further up? מקום קרנות אמה מזה
ואמה מזה. makom kranos ama mizeh v'ama mizeh.
The משנה Mishna continued that the corners, the horns, were an אמה
ama square. נמצא עשרים ושש על עשרים ושש. nimtza esrim v'shesh al
esrim v'shesh. So the top surface inside the קרנות kranos would be
twenty-six by twenty-six. Ah, so now what we really have is עשרים
ושבעה הוו. esrim v'shiva havu. What we really have is twenty-six plus
six טפחים tefachim now, right? Because we've lost another two טפחים tefachim
by our non-standard horizontal measurement. Ah, so now we're a full אמה
ama off. It's not really twenty-six, it's twenty-six plus six, which is
twenty-seven full אמות. amos So why does the משנה, Mishna, so you
want to say, okay, rounding down? We're not rounding down anymore. The
actual surface would be twenty-seven, not
twenty-six. So גמרא Gemara answers, לא דק, lo dak, it's not being
so specific. Those are really weasel answers.
Okay, but it's
around twenty-six and it's not being precise. But the
גמרא Gemara continues, the משנה Mishna continues,
מקום הילוך רגלי כהנים אמה מזה ואמה מזה. makom hiluch raglei kohanim
ama mizeh v'ama mizeh. So on the top of the מזבח, mizbe'ach
you couldn't really walk right on the edge because when you got
to the corner the קרן keren would be in the way. So
the next אמה ama interior would be the walkway around the perimeter
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach נמצא עשרים וארבע על עשרים וארבע מקום המערכה.
nimtza esrim v'arba al esrim v'arba makom hamaaracha. So the place where
the actual fire was burning was beyond that walkway. So we were
up to twenty-six and then you take away another אמה amah because
that was the width of the קרן keren and another אמה amah
for the width of the walkway, now we're up to twenty-four by
twenty-four.
עשרים וחמשה הוו. esrim v'chamisha havu. And so the גמרא Gemara says,
well it should be really twenty-five as we said
before, we already lost a full אמה amah. by the two טפח
tefach measure three times. וכי תימא הכא נמי לא דק. vechi teima
hacha nami lo dak. And so what are you going to tell
me? We already said so wasn't being so specific, right? So you're
going to tell me the same thing again? והכתיב, vehak'tiv,
but the פסוק pasuk says again, I think is this in יחזקאל?
Yechezkel והאריאל
שתים עשרה אורך בשתים עשרה רוחב רבוע אל ארבעת רבעיו.
v'ha'ariel
shteim
esreh orech b'shteim esreh rochav ravuah el arbaat rivav. The אריאל,
ariel, the place of the מזבח, mizbe'ach. was twelve by twelve.
רבוע, ravuah, was square. יכול שאינו אלא שתים עשרה על שתים עשרה.
yachol she'eino ela shteim esreh al shteim esreh. Is it really what
it means that it was only twelve by twelve? We were just
talking about twenty-four by twenty-four. כשהוא אומר אל ארבעת רבעיו, keshehu omer
el arbaat rivav, to the four sides or corners or whatever, מלמד
שבאמצע הוא מודד. melamed she'be'emtza hu moded. We're talking about twelve from
the center. So from the center to the edge of the מערכה
maaracha in each of the four directions was twelve. So that means
what? That means it was twenty-four by twenty-four measured from the outside,
right? שתים עשרה
לכל רוח ורוח. shteim esreh l'chol ruach v'ruach.
So here you can't say that the תורה Torah or that the
נביא Navi is that scripture is not being
precise. It's okay to say that
the
משנה... Mishna... וכי תימא, V'hi teima, so what are you going to
answer? Maybe you'll say שישה מינייהו מעיקרא באמה בת חמישה אזלו? Shisha
mineihu me'ikara b'ama bas chamishah izlu?
So now you'll say, well, maybe six of the שישה מינייהו מעיקרא
באמה בת חמישה אזלו, Shisha mineihu me'ikara b'ama bas chamishah izlu, maybe
six of the אמות amos that we're measuring with are the five
טפח tefach, אמות? amos So that would come out all right. אם
כן, Im kein, רב כל העזרה, rav kol ha'azarah, then we have
a problem with how the מזבח mizbe'ach, fits into the עזרה. azarah.
All right, so now, switch gears.
So we've what we've done so far is we've said, well, we
can't say that halfway up the מזבח mizbe'ach he used this measure
and then the other halfway used the other measure because it wouldn't
match up with where the center of the מזבח mizbe'ach, was relative
to the סובב. So we said okay, so the vertical of the
מזבח mizbe'ach, we're talking about six טפח אמות. amos But the horizontal,
that's where we have a problem.
Why wouldn't it fit in? It was...
Okay, so we're going to see. It's not that it wouldn't fit,
but we have specific measurements. So that's what we're going to do
now. דתנן, Detnan, כל העזרה הייתה אורך מאה ושמונים ושבע על רוחב
מאה ושלושים
וחמש ממזרח למערב. kol ha'azarah haysah orech me'ah ushmonim vesheva al rochav
me'ah ushloshim vechamesh mimizrach lema'arav. It was the whole עזרה azarah was
187 אמות amos, north to south and 135 east to west.
Where does this come from?
This is a דתנן, detnan, it's a משנה. Mishnah.
Oh, it's a משנה. Mishnah.
It's a משנה Mishnah in כלים I think.
It must be in כלים or elsewhere. Yeah. Or מידות.
Middos.
I don't see the reference here, but one of those places.
So what was that space used for? מאה ושמונים ושבע מקום דריסת
רגלי ישראל אחת עשרה אמה. me'ah ushmonim vesheva mekom drisas raglei Yisrael
achas esrei amah.
187 was where the for the regular people to walk.
Oh, sorry,
no no, I'm parsing wrong. מאה ושמונים ושבע. me'ah ushmonim vesheva. How
do you get the 187? מקום דריסת רגלי ישראל אחת עשרה אמה,
mekom drisas raglei Yisrael achas esrei amah, 11 אמה amah, for where
the where the regular people would walk. ומקום דריסת רגלי כוהנים אחת
עשרה אמה, umekom drisas raglei kohanim achas esrei amah, another 11 אמה
amah, where the כוהנים kohanim would walk. So so far 22. המזבח
שלושים ושתיים. hamizbe'ach shloshim ushtayim.
So this is obviously the key thing. 32, so that's 54. בין
האולם ולמזבח עשרים ושתיים. bein ha'ulam velamizbe'ach esrim ushtayim. Between the אולם
ulam and the מזבח mizbe'ach? was another 22, so that's 76. אמה.
amah
ההיכל מאה אמה, haheichal me'ah amah, the היכל heichal itself was 100
אמה, amah. that's 176. ועשר אמה אחורי בית הכפורת... ve'eser amah achorei
beis hakappores... really? המאה אחת עשרה, hame'ah achas esrei, it doesn't say...
ההיכל מאה אמה. haheichal me'ah amah. One second.
המאה ושמונים ושבע אמה מזבח
שלושים
ושתיים בין אולם
למזבח... ההיכל מאה אמה
haheichal me'ah
amah
and yes, sorry, correct. אחת עשרה אמה אחורי בית הכפורת achas esrei
amah achorei beis hakappores and 11 אמות behind the בית הכפורת, beis
hakappores,
more space, like the back of the היכל heichal was not right
up the wall of the עזרה, azarah, but there was another gap.
What's the בית הכפורת? beis hakappores?
The קודש הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. The כפורת kappores is the top of
the ארון. aron. So...
Yeah yeah, so here's the thing.
Here's the whole עזרה azarah and here's the היכל heichal itself, right?
We had 11 אמות for the ישראל, Yisrael, 11 אמות for the
כוהנים, kohanim, then you have 100... then there was something else, right?
There was the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Right, 32 אמות for the מזבח, then
100 אמות for the היכל heichal and another 11 אמות till the
edge of the עזרה. azarah. So that's אחורי בית הכפורת achorei beis
hakappores because here you have in the היכל heichal you have the
מנורה, menorah, the שולחן, shulchan, and the other thing, מזבח הזהב, mizbe'ach
hazahav, and then you had the ארון aron and the כפורת kappores
were in here. This is the בית הכפורת, beis hakappores, the קודש
הקודשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. And behind that was another space to the end
of the עזרה. azarah.
Okay, so the point is in figuring out all these calculations, the
מזבח was listed as how much? 32, right? Right.
אלא... Ela... so I think that's the end of the question.
So you can't say that
this אריאל Ariel can't be so big.
That's what kind of doesn't fit?
Yeah, that's right, that's right. אלא, Ela, so okay, so you can't
say that we're talking about the vertical spaces. So again, how do
we interpret this פסוק in יחזקאל Yechezkel so that he's talking about
certain which אמות were חמישה טפח אמות? chamishah tefach amos? אלא, Ela,
here's how the גמרא Gemara is going to... interpret it now. חיק
האמה בגובה, cheik ha'amah begovah, the first אמה, amah the base of
the... חיק האמה, which is the first phrase, the base was an
אמה בגובה. amah begovah. We're talking about the height. אמה רוחב כניסה.
amah rochav kenisah. The next phrase אמה רוחב amah rochav is talking
about the width of the indentation of the יסוד. גבולה אל שפתה
סביב, gevulah el sefatah saviv, when it says the border to the
end, לא שנה
הכי ולא שנה הכי, lo
shanah hachi velo
shanah hachi,
it doesn't make any difference,
it doesn't really matter, it's not that significant the difference. מזבח כמה
הוי חמישין ותמניא, mizbe'ach kamah havei chamshin vetamanya, because, oh, because that's
talking about width. Now we're going to go back to talking about
verticals, right? So מזבח כמה הוי חמישין ותמניא, mizbe'ach kamah havei chamshin
vetamanya,
so, in other words, the five טפח אמה amah was only the
first vertical אמה. amah, And the rest of it, the other nine,
were six טפח אמות. So, instead of a sixty טפח מזבח, we
have a 58,
59.
חמישין ותמניא. chamshin vetamanya.
Oh,
the top, yeah, the קרן keren was also a five טפח אמה.
amah So the bottom אמה amah and the top אמה amah. of
these ten was five טפח and the other eight were six טפח,
so we have 8 times 6 plus 2 times 5 is
58. Alright, so now does this work out with where the center
was? Let's see. פלגיה
דמזבח כמה הוי עשרין ותשעה, palgei
demizbe'ach kamah
havei esrin vetishah, so where was the center, the vertical center of
the מזבח, was 29 high, half of 58. מקרנות ועד סובב כמה
הוו, mikaranos ve'ad sovev kamah havu, from the top of the קרן
keren until the סובב, how much was it? It was עשרין ותלתא,
esrin utlata,
23, 23.
Why? Because from the קרן keren, to the סובב, the סובב was,
that's four אמות plus four full אמות plus one small אמה, amah
that's 4 times 6 is 24,
plus half of 5 is 2.5.
Maybe it's considering the top קרן, maybe it's rounding up, it seems
to me it should be
22.5, so let's call it 23. כמה בציר לפלגיה דמזבח שיתא, kamah
batzir lepalgei demizbe'ach shita, so how much between the top of the
סובב and the halfway mark on the מזבח? שיתא, shita, the difference
is six, it's דתניא מסולק למטה מרגליו ואפילו אמה אחת כשרה, detanya
mesulak lemata meraglav va'afilu amah achas kesherah,
so that works out fine
that if he put the blood even one אמה amah? below where
he was standing on top of the סובב, he would still be
above the center line of the מזבח. דיקא נמי דכתיב חיק האמה
ואמה רוחב, dayka nami dechsiv cheik ha'amah ve'amah rochav,
and this is apparent in the פסוק because it says חיק האמה
ואמה רוחב,
what we interpreted as the base was one אמה amah and the
width was one אמה. amah So that kind of fits into the
idea that the five טפח אמה amah was used for the first
אמה amah vertical and then the first indentation horizontally. שמע מינה, shema
minah, so that's how the גמרא Gemara ends up with that. We
have a few minutes, so let's continue.
וכמה אמה בינונית, vekamah amah beinonis, how much is a medium אמה?
amah, אמר רבי יוחנן ששה טפחים, amar Rabbi Yochanan shisha tefachim, six
טפחים. tefachim. אמר רב יוסף בר אבין אף אנן נמי תנינא, amar
Rav Yosef bar Avin af anan nami tanina, we also have that
in the ברייתא. braisa. רבי מאיר אומר השולחן ארכו שנים עשר ורחבו
ששה. Rabbi Meir omer hashulchan orcho shneim asar verachbo shisha. So back
to the שולחן, shulchan, Rabbi Meir says it's
12 טפחים tefachim long and 6 טפחים tefachim wide. מכלל דהוי אמה
דנפישא מינה. michlal dehavi amah denfisha minah. Oh, sorry, sorry, not מכלל.
michlal. So that's from Rabbi Meir we can see we know that
the שולחן shulchan says in the תורה Torah was one אמה amah,
by two אמות, and Rabbi Meir says which was six טפחים tefachim
by twelve טפחים, tefachim, so it's a simple calculation, each אמה amah,
that the תורה's Torah talking about which we're calling here an אמה
בינונית amah beinonis is six טפחים. tefachim. So now the גמרא Gemara
says מכלל דהוי אמה דנפישא מינה. michlal dehavi amah denfisha minah. So
you're saying it's a middle, a medium measure. What we've already seen
is a small measure what יחזקאל was referring to, it was a
five טפח אמה, amah, but if it's medium there must be a
larger one. This reminds me of the Three Billy Goats Gruff, wait
till you see my brother.
הגמרא haGemara says אין. in. Yes, that's true. והתנן, vehatnan,
but the גמרא says isn't there a משנה, Mishnah, שתי אמות היו
בשושן הבירה: shtei amos hayu bishushan habira: there were two אמה measuring
sticks in, there was a room in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
called שושן הבירה, Sushan Habira, and we'll see why it was called
that in a minute. אחת על קרן מזרחית צפונית ואחת על קרן
מזרחית דרומית. achas al keren mizrachis tzfonis veachas al keren mizrachis dromis.
One of these standard measuring sticks was in the northeast corner, one
was in the southeast corner. של קרן מזרחית צפונית, shel keren mizrachis
tzfonis, the one that was on the northeast corner, יתירה על של
משה חצי אצבע, yeseira al shel moshe chatzi etzba, was half an
אצבע etzba longer than the real אמה used by משה. Moshe.
Which they also had.
Which they had. Well, presumably that was used for the measurements of
the משכן. Mishkan. What about the, I guess,
I'm assuming that there was, this was like the standard אמה, like
it used to be the standard, the definition of a meter was
some bar kept in the, in Versailles, or some palace in France
somewhere, that was like the, now it's, it's defined by more objective
measures having to do with the vibrations of quartz, or something, that's
time, but whatever, there's some standard measure, but used to be there
was a standard meter that was the gold standard. So presumably the
same here: they had a gold standard, but the, the standards that
they kept in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, one of them was
a half a finger longer than the one, than the real one.
ושל קרן מזרחית דרומית, veshel keren mizrachis dromis, the one in the
southeast, הייתה יתירה עליה חצי אצבע. haysa yeseira aleha chatzi etzba. The
other one was a further half אצבע etzba longer. In other words,
a full אצבע. etzba. נמצאת יתירה על של משה אצבע, nimtzas yeseira
al shel moshe etzba, which means it was a full אצבע etzba
longer than the real one of משה. Moshe. ולמה אמרו אחת גדולה
ואחת קטנה? velama amru achas gedola veachas ktana? Why did they have
one a little bit longer and one a lot, even more longer?
כדי שיהיו האומנים נוטלים בקטנה ומחזירים בגדולה. kdei sheyiyu haumnim notlin biktana
umachzirim bigdola.
When the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash would need contractors, they would ask
for estimates, and the estimates would be based on the smaller measure,
but they had to deliver based on the larger measure. So this,
you know, when I first heard it I'm like, wow, this is
an abuse of power, right? But actually, the גמרא will attribute more
lofty motives. כדי שלא יבואו לידי מעילה, kdei shelo yavo’u lidei meila,
so that they would not accidentally, if you're doing something precisely and
you're a little bit off on the low side, then that means
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're stealing from the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, right. רש"י ותוספות Rashi veTosafos discuss, not רש"י ותוספות, Rashi veTosafos,
רש"י Rashi and, yeah, רש"י ותוספות Rashi veTosafos discuss whether we're talking
about like real מעילה meila or just kind of, as you said,
you know, stealing from the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or cheating the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. תרתי למה לי? tartei lama li?
So why did you have two separate measures, why wasn't it enough
just to have the one that was a little bit over, why
do you have one that was a little bit more over? You're
overcharging. Yeah, well, you're overcharging anyway, right?
But why overcharge, you're undercharging.
Well, the contractors are undercharging the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, yeah.
But if you only had the bigger one, the contractor would be
overcharging and thus cheating the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
No, no, no, in both cases, no, you have the standard one,
right? The standard one is the one, משה רבינו's Moshe Rabbeinu אמה,
that's the standard.
That's when now, I thought they used the one that's a little
bit bigger for the measurement, for the cost, and the one that's
a lot bigger for the actual measurement.
Ah, no, no, no, that's not, good, I'm glad you brought that
up. Yeah, what it's saying is that they would measure, yeah, they
would, for the cost estimate, they would use the real אמה, משה's
Moshe אמה, and for the delivery,
they would use one of these.
Yes, but it doesn't say where it was, not here anyway. There's
another one. Perhaps so. Yeah, so why do you have two different
measures that, that they would deliver on?
תרתי למה לי? tartei lama li? חדא לכספא ודהבא, chada lchaspa vedahava,
one for gold and silver things, וחדא לבניינא, vechada livinyana,
and one for like building materials. So, we didn't want, we didn't
want to take advantage of the, of the craftsmen too much, if
they were dealing with precious materials, so we don't want them to
over-deliver by a full אצבע, etzba, because that's expensive for them. So
we'll let them over-deliver by a half an אצבע, etzba, but for
building materials, you know, a little more wood or plaster, no big
deal, so let's, let's be a little more careful, or a little
more generous in our
estimation. תנן התם, tnan hasam, and we learned there, שער המזרח עליו
שושן הבירה צורה. sha’ar hamizrach alav sushan habira tzura.
The eastern gate had a picture, an engraving of שושן הבירה. Sushan
Habira. This is really strange, right?
Yeah, it is really strange.
מאי טעמא, mai ta’ama, why? רב חסדא ורב יצחק בר אבדימי, Rav
Chisda veRav Yitzchak bar Avdimi, there's a מחלוקת machlokes of רב חסדא
Rav Chisda and רב יצחק. Rav Yitzchak. חד אמר, chad amar, כדי
שידעו מהיכן באו, kdei sheyeidu meheichan ba’u, they would know where they
came from, they would remember where they came from. Look at רש"י.
Rashi.
רש"י, Rashi, right across from here,
צורה, tzura, כדי שידעו וייראו מהיכן באו. kdei sheyeidu veyeira’u meheichan ba’u.
They would be able to see that they had come back from
Persia. Obviously they stayed in Persia, ויתנו הודיה למלכות שהוציאם משם, V’yitnu
hoda’ah lamalchut shehotzi’am misham, and they would be grateful to the Persian
emperor, Persian government that allowed them to emigrate back to Israel. A
political statement. Although I do think the מהרש״א Maharsha has a different
or grateful to השם. Hashem. Well, the רש״י Rashi says הודיה למלכות
שהוציאם משם Hoda’ah lamalchut shehotzi’am misham to the Persian government. The מהרש״א
Maharsha says to God, that they would be grateful to God who
inspired or allowed the Persian authorities to let them out.
This is for the second, this is for the
second,
second בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, yes.
In the first it was called the Babylonian room.
Yeah.
וכאן אמר כדי שתהא אימת מלכות עליהן,
V’chan amar
kedei
shetehei eimat malchut aleihen, not for gratitude, but so that they would
maintain a healthy fear and respect for the government.
Who would see it?
It was on the outside. It was on the outside of the
room.
The outside of of this room.
It was like a tower on the on the or what's over
the eastern gate, שער המזרח.
Sha’ar HaMizrach.
The gate to to the עזרה. Azarah.
So who would get close enough? Only the כהנים, Kohanim, right?
No, if it was on the outside, then anybody could see it.
In the well, the the people who stayed in the עזרת נשים,
Ezras Nashim, they were able to see in there.
Yeah, well I understood that this was engraved on the outside and
I'm not sure why I thought that.
I thought it
said on the outside of of the inner עזרה, Azarah, no?
The inner עזרה. Azarah.
Not clear actually.
שער המזרח Sha’ar HaMizrach of
what? Eastern gate of the Temple is what he translates. I'm not
sure.
But the כותל Kotel was
the was not the
gate, that's on the other side, no? That's the western
side.
But of that same wall, no?
Right, the eastern is the is the main opening. Right? The Temple
faces east up to בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? Right.
But she's asking like was that the wall like what's now the
wall of the Old City or is it further in?
I'm not sure. It's it's the gate of the actual Temple itself.
But if you're in the עזרה Azarah in front of the Temple
you can see this on top of the gate.
Yeah, so I'm not sure if it was inside and even if
it was they would walk in through the southern wall, right? That's
where the steps were where the לויים Levi’im stood and then there
was a gate going into the Temple.
Right, but that's the south.
We're talking about the east side.
Didn't you walk around to the front? That's where the front is.
Well, that wall went all around, right? What wall? No, you know
you remember there was a גמרא some of the steps that would
go up people would go into the מקוה Mikveh and then people
would go in and other people would come out on the south
side, yes.
But you'd walk around to the front.
No,
they
went
into a different gate.
Different ways in. Yeah.
Yeah, there was like a main entrance.
Yes, if you brought the showbread out they didn't walk all the
way around the Temple, they brought it to the opening which is
on the east. So if you wanted to see the showbread.
You put it into the עזרה. Azarah.
Right, but on the eastern side of the Temple. So if you're
standing on the south, you're not going to see it.
Which side was the okay, we're digressing.
I mean it was on the east gate and whoever was on
the east side could see it. Whether you could see it from
where most people congregated, I'm not sure.
But certainly could be seen and whether it was seen by כהנים
Kohanim only or others.
So we don't
know which שער, Sha’ar, I don't know which שער Sha’ar it's referring
to. But whoever saw it was
yeah, but it sounds like everybody should see it to remember the
מלכות, Malchut, right?
Well yeah, but you could say the people who were in charge,
you know the leadership.
Whichever way it is, you could you could make it make sense.
It also suggests that שושן Shushan was very distinctive, because
it had a skyline or something, right? Because how what
would you know a city
from another?
Good point. Okay, let's just finish up here. אמר
רב ינאי לעולם תהא אימת מלכות עליך. Amar Rav Yannai le’olam tehei
eimat malchut alecha. You should always have fear of the government. שנאמר
וירדו כל עבדיך אלה אלי והשתחוו לי לאמר. She’ne’emar ve’yardu kol avadecha
eileh elai vehishtachavu li leimor.
משה Moshe said to פרעה Paroh when he warned him about the
tenth plague, all of your servants will come down to me and
bow down to me and beg for us to leave. But he
said your servants, he didn't say you will come down to me.
That was out of אימת מלכות. eimat malchut. He was demonstrating a
little a little bit of of fear like he's not going to
directly oppose פרעה Paroh himself. ואילו לדידי לא. V’ilu ledidi lo. He
didn't say that you will come down. לא קאמר ליה. Lo ka’amar
lei. רבי יוחנן אמר מהכא. Rabbi Yochanan amar meihacha. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan brings another פסוק for אימת מלכות. eimat malchut. שנאמר ויד ה׳
היתה אל אליהו וישנס מתניו. She’ne’emar veyad Hashem hayetah el Eliyahu vayeshannes
matnav. The hand of God came to אליהו Eliyahu and he he
prepared. prepared himself to travel, וירץ לפני אחאב עד בוא יזרעאל, vayaratz
lifnei Achav ad bo Yizreel, and he ran before אחאב Achav until
יזרעאל. Yizreel. רש"י Rashi says that he, אחאב, Achav, was riding along,
and it's not כבוד המלכות, kavod hamalchus, so to demonstrate his respect
for מלכות, malchus, אליהו Eliyahu accompanies him all that way. Okay, this
is a place to stop.
יישר כח. yasher koach. This is really trying to recreate and
to put you there.